A Guide to the Papers of John Linn Hurt, 1804-1931
Special Collections, University of Virginia Library
Special Collections, University of Virginia Library
Papers of John Linn Hurt 1755-1931
Special Collections, University of Virginia Library
38-86, 38-86-a
This collection consists of ca. 5,000 items. (ca. 11 shelf feet).
Administrative Information
Access Restrictions
There are no restrictions.
Acquisition Information
This collection was a gift of the Hurt Family of Chatham, Va., 1930-1931, 1937, and 1959.
Biographical/Historical Information
John Linn Hurt was born in 1838, in Carrroll County, Tennessee, and raised in Halifax County, Virginia. He was the son of William Walker Hurt, a Halifax farmer, and Nancy Sims Linn. His earliest American Ancestor was the Reverend Philomen Hurt, a Baptist minister who was born in Virginia in 1785.
Hurt was educated at the Samuel Davis Institute at Halifax Courthouse, Virginia. He was given his first job there by James Easley in 1854, as deputy of the Halifax Clerk's office. After three years at this job, Hurt became clerk of Pittsylvania County. The relationship with Easley continued, and led to the establishment of the Hurt fortune. Their financial collaboration began when Easley asked Hurt to mange lands in Missouri for him at about the time of the Civil War. While doing so, Hurt also began investing in land for himself. Easley and Hurt remained business partners until the former's death in 1881. In 1861, Hurt enlisted as a Confederate soldier and rose to the rank of Colonel. In 1862 he was captured and exchanged, after which time he returned to Pittsylvania. Around 1870, John Hurt, together with his brother, Henry Hays Hurt, became involved with the management of Hurt's store in Pittsylvania. During this same period, Hurt was in charge of the division of Pittsylvania County in to townships, and of the establishment there of public education and U.S. postal service.
In 1877, Hurt was elected to the state senate, a post which he held continuously until approximately 1905, eventually assuming leadership as senate president. Hurt's contemporaries considered him a shrewd politician. He was a conservative Democrat and a principal opponent of William Mahone and the Readjuster Party. Mahone led the Readjusters to almost complete control of the Virginia state government during the brief period, 1879-1883, in which the party flourished. The Readjusters favored scaling down or repudiating Virginia's Civil War debt in order to finance public services, while the Conservatives reversed these priorities.
After retiring from public life, Hurt settled on his estate in Pittsylvania County immersed himself in his personal affairs and friendships until his death, at the age of ninety-three, in 1931. He was married twice, first to Nannie Kate Clement in 1862 (d. 1872) and then to Sallie T. Douglas in 1874. He had no children by either marriage.
Henry Hays Hurt was born in 1842. He became sheriff of Halifax County in 1863. It appears that he too served in the Civil War, as he is often addressed as Captain Hurt. H.H. Hurt was the principle operator of Hurt's store.
Scope and Content
The Hurt Papers at the University of Virginia comprise ca. 5,000 items (ca. 11 shelf feet) dating from 1755-1931, with most material dated after 1850. The material consists chiefly of the correspondence and business papers of John L. Hurt, and ledgers and daybooks from Hurt's store.
The material in accession numbers 38-86 and 38-86-a, now combined, consist of ca. 4900 items, dating from 1809-1831, although most of the material is post 1850. They consist chiefly of the correspondence and business papers of John L. Hurt, and the correspondence of H.H. Hurt.
The correspondence of John L. Hurt regards his wartime imprisonment and exchange in 1862, his political career beginning in 1877, and his personal business, family and friends. The political letters include accounts of Hurt's attempt to become governor of Virginia in 1885, letters from Senator John W. Daniel (beginning n 1885) and Hurt's 1908 account of the intrigue surrounding the defeat of the Readjuster Party in 1879. The personal business papers mainly concerns investment and debts, including large investments in Panama Canal bonds (ca. 1912) and in Liberty Bonds. There are letters from the laboratory of Thomas Edison (1892) and from the offices of Presidents Grover Cleavland (1892) and Theodore Roosevelt (1908).
The correspondence of Henry Hays Hurt deals chiefly with retail and legal matters. His election to the Virginia state senate in 1875 is documented by letters of congratulation. Personal correspondence includes letters from brothers John L. Hurt, S.S. Hurt, and William Hurt.
The financial and legal papers of John L. Hurt include records of his assets, investments, and debts. A large portion of the papers relate to Hurt's store, including many receipts from wholesalers. Also included are postal records, and a book of debts to George H. West and Co. dated 1867.
Miscellaneous papers in the collection include genealogical materials of John L. Hurt, verse written by him and early papers (1809-1848) form his files. The collection also includes account books, photographs, printed material, and four ledgers. These collections are a gift of the Hurt family, Chatham, Virginia, October 1959, and bear no restrictions.
Arrangement
The collection has been divided into the following seven series, each arranged chronologically:
Series I. Correspondence:
Subseries A. John L. Hurt
Subseries B. H.H. Hurt
Series II. Financial and legal papers of John L. Hurt
Series III. Miscellaneous papers of John L. Hurt (including genealogical material and verse)
Series IV. Account books
Series V. Photographs
Series VI. Printed Material
Series VII. Ledgers
Contents List
- Series I: Correspondence
  - Subseries A. Correspondence of John L. Hurt
    - Correspondence of John L. Hurt, 12 folders 1835-1922 (Box 1)
    - Correspondence of John L. Hurt, 7 folders 1923-1931, n.d. (Box 2)
  - Subseries B. Correspondence of H.H. Hurt
    - Correspondence of H.H. Hurt, 3 folders 1867-1871 (Box 2)
    - Correspondence of H.H. Hurt 1867-1874 (Box 3)
    - Letters to N.M. Wilson and Co.from W.G. Morton, Jr. 1873 (Box 3)
    - Correspondence of H.H. Hurt, 7 folders 1875-1882,nd (Box 3)
- Series II: Financial and legal papers of John L. Hurt
  - Financial aand legal papers of John L.Hurt, 5 Folders 1804[1850]- (Box 3)
  - 1857 (Box 3)
  - Financial and legal papers of John L. Hurt, 12 folders 1858-1865 (Box 4)
  - Finanfcial and legal papers of John L. Hurt, 10 folders 1866-1872 (Box 5)
  - Financial and legal papers of John L. Hurt, 3 folders 1873-1878 (Box 6)
  - Bundled receipts and cancelled checks of John L. Hurt 1877-1890 (Box 6)
  - Financial and legal papers of John L. Hurt, 7 folders 1879-1915 (Box 6)
  - Financial and legal papers of John L. Hurt, 8 folders 1916-1931,n.d. (Box 7)
- Series III: Miscellaneous papers of John L. Hurt
  - George Robertson- Bond to Governor John Tyler 1809 (Box 7)
  - Copy of Certificate of William Fry, taken from Franklin County Register 1815 (Box 7)
  - Edmund Tucker's Crop of Tobacco 1818 (Box 7)
  - Copy of registers of Pollk and Burwell Going, from Pittsylvania County register 1824;1837 (Box 7)
  - Deed 1826 (Box 7)
  - Register of Henry Reynolds 1827 (Box 7)
  - Ledger Sheet 1831 (Box 7)
  - Thomas L. Spraggins Account 1832 (Box 7)
  - Indenture and receipt 1843 (Box 7)
  - Hiram Elder Bond and P. Taylor receipt 1844 (Box 7)
  - William Neal Statement to Elijah D. Hundley 1845 (Box 7)
  - Bonds, statements, indentures 1846-1848 (Box 7)
  - Papers concerning property of G.A. Carter 1871-1876 (Box 7)
  - Election ballots 1907 Nov (Box 7)
  - Election Ballots 1912 Nov (Box 7)
  - Genealogical papers of John L. Hurt n.d. (Box 8)
  - Verse by John L. Hurt n.d. (Box 8)
  - Petition opposing re-election of William M. Tredway n.d. (Box 8)
  - Miscellaneous fragments, incomplete forms, ect. n.d. (Box 8)
- Series IV: Account Books n.d. (Box 8)
  Miscellaneous account books
- Series V: Photographs n.d. (Box 8)
  Photographs
- Series VI: Printed Material
  - Newspaper clippings of JohnL.Hurt ca. 1880-1935 (Box 8)
  - Phamplets from John L. Hurt papers n.d. (Box 8)
  - Virginia House Bills n.d. (Box 8)
  - Birthday cards, 2 folders n.d. (Box 8)
- Series VII: Ledgers
  - County or personal business 1866 (Box 9)
  - County or personal business 1868-1892 (Box 9)
  - Retail accounts includes 1896 inventory 1896-1901 (Box 9)
  - Tobacco Accounts kept by J.J. Reynolds 1896-1901 (Box 9)